## PETER R. SHEPLER

10624 Sussex Square N. • Mint Hill, NC 28227 prshepler1@aol.com • (C) 330-608-6833 • linkedin.com/in/prshepler

### **BUSINESS PROFESSIONAL**

Expertise in prospecting new business, account development, collecting customer requirements, strategic planning, and customer presentations. Effective in building relationships of long standing. Engineering background enables understanding how things work. Business experience applies to identifying customer needs and aligning products and services to meet requirements. Experienced world traveler.

## Competencies include:

- Account management Project timing, product delivery, relationship building
- **Program management** Budgeting, project management
- Sales USA & Global customer base
- Business planning New technology, ROI forecasts, customer acquisition
- Marketing Website content, educational webinars, tradeshows
- Startup companies Establish and activate sales and marketing
- **Product testing** Laboratory, field, regulatory
- Team management, hiring and development Recognized for high levels of "engagement"
- **Regulation** compliance Secured multiple testing contracts with government agencies
- Race tire engineering, track support, and manufacturing 12 US Patents for tire design

BSME, Clarkson College of Technology, Potsdam, NY

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Product Director, CAMBER RIDGE, LLC, Charlotte, NC (2016 – Present)

Camber Ridge, LLC is a startup company developing a new method to measure tire performance. Broad startup responsibilities to establish processes, customer acquisition, marketing and sales.

- Product: Focused R&D to develop (prioritize) customer valued services based on sales volume.
- Process: Selected, populated, and deployed CRM system, Responsible for price quotations.
- Marketing: Website content, email updates, technical presentations at conferences
- Sales: Developed value based pricing and selling argument for services based on competitor analysis
- Customer: Created sales presentations, contacted target customers and delivered message globally

### Business Development Manager, SMITHERS RAPRA, Akron, Ohio (2012 – 2015)

Smithers Rapra provides independent third party tire and wheel testing services. Responsibilities include sales, new customer acquisition, business planning, and key account management to serve a global mix of tire, vehicle, and wheel manufacturers, tire and wheel distributors, and government agencies.

- \$8.5M in annual sales across 3 business units, Increased revenue 30% year over year (2012, 2013)
- Created business partnership to provide complete tire models (data and fitting) to OEM industry
- Successfully negotiated multi-year government contracts for tire testing services (NHTSA, EPA)

PETER R. SHEPLER Page 2

## **Principal, GOFA OPPORTUNITIES LLC,** Stow, Ohio (2010 – 2011)

Project based services linking new technology products to the marketplace. Focus on small companies requiring business development for emerging technologies, service expansion and funding.

- Business case assessment for tire/vehicle simulation expansion "Stackpole Engineering Services"
- Product development and initial sales for Nutek Green

### THE GOODYEAR TIRE & RUBBER COMPANY, Akron, Ohio

# Project Leader, Technology and Innovation Strategy Planning (2009 to 2010)

Leader of "transformation" projects to establish the Innovation Creation Process (ICP). Market back approach prioritized global marketing input to define tire technology development programs.

• Deployed new supplier innovation process connecting supplier solutions to business needs.

## Manager, Goodyear Vehicle Systems (2001 to 2009)

Formed and managed a new international team with the competence to develop sensor and memory systems that integrate tires electronically into vehicle operating systems.

- Bus tire leasing trial using RFID tagging reduced billing cycle by 1 month
- Truck TPMS/Telematics trial linking low pressure warning to service center.
- Negotiated and lead business development activities in a JDA with Siemens VDO Automotive to develop and market the "Tire IQ" intelligent tire
- Deployed RFID enabled tire information system for NASCAR tire leasing operation.

# Chief Engineer, Advanced Race Tire Development (1999 to 2001)

Leader of the technical teams responsible for Indy-car tire development and tire/vehicle simulation.

- Successfully met a 20-race schedule by managing a fast-paced development program in a short lead time production environment
- Supported vehicle performance simulations with advanced tire models and analysis

#### Account Manager, General Motors Account (1993 to 1999) - Detroit, Michigan

Tire Engineering for largest OEM account. Effective relationship building with marketing and vehicle development organizations, developing trust and credibility with the vehicle engineers and solving ride and handling problems with new tire designs, achieving 26 new tire engineering approvals.

### Senior Engineer, Formula-1 and IndyCar (1980 to 1993)

Designer in bias to radial tire design conversion. Developed design rules and established lab durability requirements. Specialist in tire mold shapes and rain tire tread designs. Traveled to races to provide engineering support to assigned teams. Contributed to 4 Formula-1 championships, 7 Indy 500 victories

# Tire Designer, Runflat Tires.

Innovated patented "sidewall sandwich" tire technology doubling runflat mileage distance.

#### TRAINING

Kellogg School of Management: Creating and Managing Strategic Alliances
University of Michigan: Finance for the Non-Financial Manager
ESI International: Project Planning Analysis and Control
Preston G Smith: Flexible Product Development
Kottler Group: Defending Price